A Guide to the Records of the Public Foundry at Westham, 1776-1789.
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of the Public Foundry at Westham,
1776-1789.
The Library of Virginia
54304
Public Foundry.
6 volumes and .2 cubic feet.
These records are part of the Revolutionary War / Government record group (R.G. 2)
Administrative Information
Arranged alphabetically.
Access Restrictions
Use microfilm when available.
Acquisition Information
Acquired prior to 1905.
Historical Information
On May 22, 1776, the fifth revolutionary convention approved a petition that had been submitted by John Ballendine and John Reveley proposing to construct a cannon foundry and a blast furnace for the manufacture of ordnance. A site at Westham, near Richmond, was purchased and construction began immediately. When it was completed, the foundry complex included eight blast furnaces, a boring mill, and the foundry, besides all the buildings necessary to house workers and store supplies. The buildings were burned by Lt. Col. John G. Simcoe and his troops on January 5, 1781, in association with Benedict Arnold's raid on Richmond. The foundry functioned intermittently until the war ended, when operations ceased altogether.
Scope and Content
Public Foundry at Westham records include: Account book of John Reveley, 1779-1781 and account papers, 1776-1789; Journal, 1779-1781; and Ledgers (3), 1776-1781, with an Index, 1779-1781.
Journals and ledgers record cash disbursements for foundry supplies (iron, coal, gunpowder), building materials and work, provisions for workers, wages and the hiring of wagons and enslaved individuals. Ledgers include accounts with individuals as well as separate account headings for Boring Mill, Bricklayer Work, Buckingham Furnace, Cannon, Carpentry, Coal, Fire Bricks, Gunpowder, Negroes (p. 42), Pitt Coal, Provisions, Shoemaking, Wages, and Waggonage.
For additional records see the Governor's Executive Papers for this time period; and Public Foundry at Westham records of the Auditor of Public Accounts, 1771-1792 (APA 662).
Contents List
- Account book of John Revely and account papers, 1776-1789., Extent: 1 volume and .2 cubic feet
  Account book of John Revely, 1779 Mar-1781 Mar, includes entries for individual accounts. Account papers, 1776-1789 and undated, include loose accounts and receipts related to Foundry operations. Includes several items documenting the hiring of enslaved individuals to work at the Foundry, including the names of the enslaved individuals as well as the name of the enslaver.
  - Account book of John Revely, 1779 Mar-1781 Mar. (Box 1)
  - Accounts, 1776. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Accounts, 1777. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Accounts, 1778. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Accounts, 1779. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Accounts, 1780. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Accounts, 1781. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Accounts, 1782. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Accounts, 1783. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Accounts, 1784. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Accounts, 1785. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Accounts, 1786. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Accounts, 1789. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Accounts, undated. (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Journal, 1779 Feb 1-1781 May 9., Extent: 1 v.
  This journal provides a daily, chronological recording of cash disbursements, with notations to ledgers.
  Also available on Miscellaneous Reel 638.
- Ledgers, 1776-1781., Extent: 4 volumes.
  Ledgers provide a record of cash disburements by individual account. Individual accounts are in no discernable order. There is some overlapping of dates among the volumes.
  This volume is arranged chronologically and there is no index.
  - Ledger, 1776 July 15-1779 Jan.
  - Ledger, 1776 July 15-1781 Nov 19.
  - Ledger, 1779 Feb 1-1781 June 19.
  - Ledger - Index, 1779-1781.
- Letterbooks, 1780 July 21-1982 Dec 2., Extent: 8 v.
  Letterbooks include copies of the outgoing correspondence of the War Office. While there are no gaps, there is some overlapping of dates in the volumes. All volumes except for Letterbook, 1780 July 21-1781 Jan 2, are indexed. The separate index volume indexes WAR volumes 55-59 (designating them with letters B, C, F, E, and G respectively).
  Letterbook, 1781-1786, includes War Office, 1781 Dec 24-1782 Dec 2; and Council of State, 1782 Dec 24-1786 July 12.
  Also available on Miscellaneous Reels 632-633, and 990-992.
  - Letterbook (no index), 1780 July 21-1781 Jan 2. (Volume 1)
  - Letterbook (WAR 54), 1781 Jan 18-Sept 1. (Volume 2)
  - Letterbook (WAR 55, B), 1781 Aug 15-Nov 1. (Volume 3)
  - Letterbook (WAR 56, C), 1781 Nov 2-1782 Jan 22. (Volume 4)
  - Letterbook (WAR 59, F) - War Office and Council of State Journal, 1781 Dec 24-1782 Dec 2; 1782 Dec 24-1786 July 12. (Volume 5)
  - Letterbook (WAR 58, E), 1782 Jan 22-May 5. (Volume 6)
  - Letterbook (WAR 57, G), 1782 May 6-Oct 12. (Volume 7)
  - Index, 1781 Aug 15-1786 July 12. (Volume 8)